Collection of Ephemera Relating to the Marketing of Books, 1742-2014: Finding Aid
Princeton University Library. Department of Rare Books and Special Collections.
- Publishing Ephemera Dated In the 1900s, 1900-1999; 11 boxes (10 partial)
  - (A) frictionless (. g(new)ru(year)2(u), 1987; 38450; portion of 1 box
    Single sheet folded into 8-sided pamphlet, 8vo; illustrations; printed in brown and grey or tan paper. "Here is the one hundred eleventh small volume from this press."
  - Hamady, Walter: Gabberjæb number (6), 1988; 38451; portion of 1 box
    Broadside, folio (311 mm.); printed on tan paper; previous folds, else fine. At head of title: Neopostmod(rin)ism (pr) dieser rasen ist kein hundeklo (or) guberzompthin...(or) the incognita of Rita's deep time coexisting within central discoveries of the thermodynamic dichotomy of Western thought: by Wsh (the) Hamady."
  - Hall, Edwin: Sweynheym and Pannartz and the origins of printing in Italy: German technology and Italian humanism in Renaissance Rome, 1991; 38355; portion of 1 box
    Author: Hall, Edwin
    McMinnville, Oregon: Phillip J. Pirages
    Single sheet folded into 6-sided pamphlet, 8vo; color photographic illustrations; fine. Prospectus for a work printed at the Bird & Bull Press, limited to 239 copies; integral order form.
  - Margo Egdon: Margo for the millenia, [1999?]; portion of 1 box
    Author: Margo Egdon
    Little Rock, AK: Pasquinade Press
    Broadside. Black lettering with the middle of the O filled in with light blue.
  - Voretzsch, Karl: Sammlung kurzer lehrbücher der romanischen sprachen und literaturen, 1913; 39354; portion of 1 box
    Author: Voretzsch, Karl
    Halle (Saale): Max Niemeyer Verlag.
    Broadside, 8vo (220 mm.); toned along edges, previous fold. Prospectus printed in German.
  - Paul, Hermann: Altdeutsche textbibliothek, 1925; 39302; portion of 1 box
    Author: Paul, Hermann
    Halle (Saale): Max Niemeyer.
    Broadside, small 8vo (190 mm.); uniformly toned, previous fold, else a very good copy. Text in German.
  - The Nonesuch Press announces, on alternate Wednesdays from October 6 to December 15, at 5:30 P/M., in the Wigmore Hall a series of six period concerts, 1580 to the present day, 1925; 36445; portion of 1 box
    Cambridge: The Nonesuch Press
    Bifolium, 8vo; a series of concerts "offered as illustrations in the history of music". Information on tickets provided on the back page. Advance order form loosely inserted. Discoloration, top right-hand corner torn, not affecting text.
  - A selected list of books for Christmas gifts, 1930; 39411; portion of 1 box
    Single sheet folded into 6-sided pamphlet, 8vo; 2-toned illustration (red and black); previous fold, else fine. Titles include Githa Sowerby's retelling of "Cinderella" and Stanley Casson's "Some Modern Sculptors". Integral order form.
  - Marshall, Archibald: The novels, 1930; 39209; portion of 1 box
    Author: Marshall, Archibald
    Minneapolis: Powers Mercantile Company
    Bifolium, square 12mo; previous fold, near fine. Prospectus for a uniform set of Marshall's novels, which, not to read them is "nowadays...considered bad form by those who keep abreast of the times in the literary world". List of titles provided on back.
  - Audubon, John James: Audubon's the birds of America, 1930; 39210; portion of 1 box
    Minneapolis: Powers Dry Goods Co.
    Broadside, folio (311 mm.); previous fold, else fine. Prospectus for an edition "available to the general public," with introduction by William Vogt. Specimen page (plate 102, Blue Jay), printed on verso.
  - Williams, Sidney Herbert and Falconer Madan: A handbook of the literature of the Rev. C.L. Dodgson (Lewis Carroll), 1931; 39406; portion of 1 box
    Author: Williams, Sidney Herbert and Falconer Madan
    Bifolium, 8vo; reduced facsimiles; previous folds, toning. Prospectus for a work "To lovers of 'Alice,'" published in an edition of 750 copies. Provides specimen pages and facsimiles; integral order form printed on back.
  - Whitman, Walt: Leaves of grass, 1943; 38585; portion of 1 box
    New York: Peter Pauper Press
    Biofolium, folio; black and white photographic illustration; previous fold, else fine. Call for sponsors for the Mid-Century Commemorative Edition of Whitman's masterpiece. Enrollment form laid in.
  - Kronenberg, M.E., F.K.H. Kossmann, L. Brummel, eds.: Het boek, 1944; 39225; portion of 1 box
    Author: Kronenberg, M.E., F.K.H. Kossmann, L. Brummel, eds.
    The Hague: Martinus Nihjoff
    Broadside, 8vo (250 mm.); woodcut illustration; printed in red and black; previous fold, else fine. Prospectus for volume XXXII of "the only Netherlands journal for bibliographers and booklovers".
  - Oxford editions of standard authors, 1947; 39404; portion of 1 box
    London: Oxford University Press
    Single sheet folded into 6-sided pamphlet, 12mo; fine. Featured authors include Dante, Milton, and Sir Walter Scott. Distributed by Frank Hollings, London.
  - The return to fundamentals. An explanation of the purposes and ideals of the Powgen Press, 1950; 38346; portion of 1 box
    New York: Powgen Press
    Bifolium, 8vo; text printed in black and gilt; previous fold, else fine. Short mission statement from the Press: "Two fundamentals are always observed: first, that every piece of printing must always be thoroughly appropriate in design as well as competent in execution; and, second, that the buyer of printing must have, at all times, the fullest cooperation in meeting the demands for excellence at prices in keeping with the modern budget".
  - Jennett, Seán: The making of books, 1951; 37103; portion of 1 box
    Author: Jennett, Seán
    New York: Pantheon Books Inc.
    Broadside, 8vo (215 mm.); illustrated prospectus for "a fresh survey of the many processes that transform an author's manuscript into a finished book". Contents provided; integral order form. Previous folds.
  - Hearst, James: Limited view, 1960; 38517; portion of 1 box
    Author: Hearst, James
    Broadside, folio (303 mm.); text printed in red and black; previous folds, else fine. Prospectus for this poetry collection in which the poet "is concerned, as always, with no particular poetic movement or school; his cast of thought and mode of expression are peculiarly his own." Integral order form on Broadside verso.
  - Lingenfelter, Richard E.: Presses of the Pacific Islands, 1817-1867. A history of the first half century of printing in the Pacific Island, 1970; 38500; portion of 1 box
    Author: Lingenfelter, Richard E.
    Los Angeles: Plantin Press
    Bifolium, 8vo; fine. "In this book Richard E. Lingenfelter sketches the early history of printing in each of the island groups, drawing principally from the letters, diaries, journals and reminiscences of the missionaries and other visitors to the islands." Illustrated with woodcuts by Edgar Dorsey Taylor; limited to 500 copies and distributed by Dawson's Bookshop.
  - Titles in print (old & new) as of Independence Day, 1980; 38475; portion of 1 box
    Broadside, 4to (267 mm.); previous folds, else fine. List of titles with price and binding information.
  - Why did you didn/t. Expanded quotables, 1980; 38476; portion of 1 box
    Broadside, oblong 16mo (106 x 151 mm.); mostly fine. Postcard prospectus for a sequal book of quotes made by local school children.
  - Moser, Barry: A selection of nine wood engravings, 1980; 38421; portion of 1 box
    Bifolium, large folio; 9 reduced reproductions of above-mentioned wood engravings; previous folds, else fine. Integral order form.
  - Kherdian, David: Homage to Adana, 1980; 38474; portion of 1 box
    Author: Kherdian, David
    Broadside, 4to (261 mm.); illustration printed in blue; text in red and black. Prospectus for an edition limited to 120 press-numbered copies.
  - Oppenheimer, Joel: Del quien lo tomó. A suite, 1982; 38471; portion of 1 box
    Author: Oppenheimer, Joel
    Broadside, oblong 16mo (89 x 139 mm.); fine. Postcard prospectus for a collection of 3 poems in an edition of 228 copies.
  - Moser, Barry: An unillustrated talk on illustrating books, 1985; 36384; portion of 1 box
    Northhampton, Massachusetts: Pennyroyal Press
    Single sheet, folded into 8-sided brochure; prospectus for the "Pennyroyal Lectures" by Barry Moser, which also include "Illustrating the Classics: Homer, Virgin, and Dante"; "On Illustrating Books"; "Frankstein"; Eryngium and the White Knight's Horse"; "On Wood Engraving"; "The Books of Pennyroyal Press"; "Illustrating Alice"; "On Books"; "Moby-Dick"; "Huckleberry Finn"; "The Wizard of Oz"; "A Personal Approach to the Design and Illustration of Books".
  - Reynolds comprehensive atlas and gazetteer of the world. Including 1920 census, 1921; 38598; portion of 1 box
    Minneapolis: Powers
    Single sheet folded into 6-sided pamphlet, 16mo; color illustration; mostly fine. Prospectus for "The most useful book in the world"; provides a partial list of the book's features and press comments.
  - Byvanck, A.W. et G.J. Hoogewerff: La miniature hollandaise et les manuscrits illustrés du 14e au 16e siècle aux Pay-bas septentrionaux, 1923; 38317; portion of 1 box
    Author: Byvanck, A.W. et G.J. Hoogewerff
    La Haye: Martinus Nijhoff
    Bifolium, large folio; text in red and black; previous folds, else fine. Prospectus for the French edition of this work (advertisement for the English edition, "Dutch Miniatures in Manuscripts of the 14th, 15th and 16th Centuries" printed on back). Edition limited to 300 copies; integral order form.
  - Nijhoff, W.: L'art typographique dans les Pays-bas, 1926; 38314; portion of 1 box
    Author: Nijhoff, W.
    La Haye: M. Nijhoff
    8vo, unpaginated; facsimiles throughout; previous folds, else fine. Prospectus text by Emile H. van Heurck.
  - Announcing the first American publications, 1926; 39372; portion of 1 box
    New York: Pegasus Press.
    Bifolium, 8vo; blue decorative borders; previous fold, else fine. List of titles now availabe in the United States, including Tancred Borenius and E.W. Tristram's "English Mediaeval Painting"; and Stanley Morison's "The Moyllius Alphabet". Prospectus distributed by the Continental Typefounders Association.
  - A Portrait in Natural Colour of the Nonesuch Dickens., 1937?; portion of 1 box
    Nonesuch Press.
    Pamplet with staples on the spine. Contains the same color photo of the Nonesuch Dickens as the lavendar booklets pasted in.
  - Dickens, Charles: The Nonesuch Dickens, 1938; 39250; portion of 1 box
    8vo, mixed paginations; color photographic folding plate; original green-grey pictorial wrappers, mostly fine. A collection of sample pages and illustrations from the Nonesuch edition of Dickens's works. Order form laid in.
  - Carroll, Lewis: The hunting of the snark. With illustrations in color by Edward A. Wilson, 1939; 38582; portion of 1 box
    Bifolium, large 8vo; printed on green paper, text in purple and black; fine. Prospectus for this limited edition of 275 copies. Specimen page provided.
  - Baldwin, Hanson W.: The Navy at war. Paintings and drawings by combat artists by special arrangement with the Navy Department...Introduction by Admiral A.J. Hepburn, 1943; 38340; portion of 1 box
    Author: Baldwin, Hanson W.
    Minneapolis: Power's
    Bifolium, 4to; color illustration reproduction of a watercolor, "Air Defense (in the Battle of Santa Cruz)" by Lieutenant Dwight C. Shepler"; previous folds, else fine. Prospectus for an illustrated work with pieces by Lieutenant Commander Griffith Baily Coale, Lieutenant Shepler, Lieutenant William F. Draper, Lieutenant (jg) Mitchell Jamieson, and Lieutenant Albert K. Murray. Integral order form.
  - Books for our time. Book design in today's world, 1951; 39425; portion of 1 box
    Bifolium, large 4to; illustration; printed on yellow paper; prevous folds, else fine. Prospectus for this exhibition catalogue; provides table of contents and index.
  - Profiles through the ages. A graphic alphabet of genius, 1953; 38343; portion of 1 box
    New York: Profile Press
    Single sheet folded into 6-sided pamphlet, small 8vo; 2 illustrated specimen pages; previous fold, else fine. Prospectus of a work "for those who cherish history...for those who are in love with typography," to be distributed by Museum Books.
  - William Morris and the art of the book, 1976; 39422; portion of 1 box
    Broadside, 16mo (152 mm.); illustration; fine. Prospectus for a work "intended to celebrate the accomplishment of one of the foremost men in the history of the printing arts," based on the Pierpont Morgan Library exhibition. Accompanied by an order form and a photocopied letter announcng the publication.
  - [William IX, Duke of Aquitaine]: Guillem de Poitou, his eleven extant poems translated by Paul Blackburn, edited and foreward by George Economou & two title page drawings by Roland Ginzel, 1976; 38440; portion of 1 box
    Author: [William IX, Duke of Aquitaine]
    Mt. Horeb, Wisc.: Perishable Press
    Broadside, 4to (292 mm.); illustration printed in grey; fine. Prospectus for this edition limited to 165 copies considered by the Press "the most elegant title to date".
  - Lanyon, Ellen, illust.: Squatting flies/quotables...calligraphy by Michael Hughey, 1981; 38444; portion of 1 box
    Author: Lanyon, Ellen, illust.
    Bifolium, square 12mo; illustration; printed on grey-green paper; fine. Prospectus of a compilation of observations made by 16 schoolchildren; edition limited to 200 copies.
  - The Oxford library of the world's great books. Patron's edition, 1982; 39430; portion of 1 box
    Large 4to, unpaginated; color photographic illustrations; original grey gilt wrappers, fine. Order form and typed letter on Press letterhead laid in. Special offer provided by American Express.
  - Wakoski, Diane: Cut-back & the End, 1989; portion of 1 box
    Beige long and narrow Broadside announcing new mailing list. With envelope.
  - Burdick, Laura: A tapestry of languages, 1994; 37015; portion of 1 box
    Author: Burdick, Laura
    Los Angeles: Occidental College Tiger Press
    Bifolium, large 8vo; prospectus for a work "printed by the author as an advanced student project". "This book is a highly visual collage of Spanish, Armenian, Arabic, Japanese, and Russian translations of a Ralph Ellison quotation." Edition limited to 55 copies.
  - A little journey thru the world's finest newspaper plant. The new home of the Pittsburgh Press, a Scripps-Howard Newspaper, 1927; 45446; portion of 1 box
    Pittsburgh: Pittsburgh Press
    Oblong 8vo, unpaged; plain photographic illustrations throughout, text and typographical decorations printed in blue and orange; original stiff white pictorial staplebound wrappers (a few soil spots); very good. An attractive little promotional pamphlet for both the Plant and the Press. SMU only in OCLC as of May, 2014.
  - Die Propyläen kunstgeschichte, 1960; 44697; portion of 1 box
    Berlin: Propyläen-Verlag.
    Small 4to, unpaged; staplebound pictorial self-wrappers (foxing along edges); 2 plates of illustrations printed on rectos and versos, additional illustrations in text; some wear from handling, else very good. Order form bound in. Text in German.
  - For Nearly Five Centuries, 1953; portion of 1 box
    Oxford University Press.
    Bifolium. A short history of the press writted by Hellmut Lehmann-Haupt. Reproduction part of the press' first printed book on the outside of the booklet.
  - Ferguson, John: Museums. Their history & their uses…Three Volumes in two... With a 700p. Bibliography., 1999; portion of 1 box
    Bifolium, 8vo; black and white illustrations; fine. Prospectus for a history of museums and collecting; provides the table of contents, a list of the collectors and collections discussed, and topics essayed. Edition limited to 250 copies.
  - Ferguson, John: Revised index. Bibliographical notes on histories of inventions & books of secrets. New foreword by William Eamon, 1998; portion of 1 box
    Bifolium, 8vo; text printed in orange and black.
  - Ferguson, John: An Essential Reference. Bibliographical notes on histories of inventions & books of secrets. New foreword by William Eamon., 1998; portion of 1 box
  - Welty, Eudora: The robber bridegroom. Designed and illustrated by Barry Moser, 1987; 36382; portion of 1 box
    8vo, single sheet folded twice, uncut; "The text is set in 12 point Dante, designed by the archtypographer Giovanni Mardersteig and composed Monotype by Michael and Winifred Bixler at their typofoundry in Skaneateles, New York. The book was printed on Mohawk letterpress by Harold P. McGrath in an edition of one hundred and fifty copies signed by both Moser and Welty. It is bound in full leather."
  - Dear Pennyroyal Friends, 1987; portion of 1 box
    Typewritten letter to Pennyroyal customers.
  - Murray, David: Museums. Their history & their uses...New introduction by Paul Findlen, 1999; 39295; portion of 1 box
    Author: Murray, David
    Staten Island: Pober Publishing.
  - Allen, Hervey: Bedford village, 1944; 38341; portion of 1 box
    Author: Allen, Hervey
    Bifolium, 8vo; color illustration titled "...1764 on the Pennsylvania Frontier"; fine. Prospectus for a novel of Colonial America, part of the series beginning with The Disinherited and a sequal to The Forest and the Fort. Integral order form.
  - October House Classics, 1957; 42467; 2 copies of booklet, only 1 of Broadside
    New Fairfield, CT: October House.
    Bifolium, small 8vo; fine. Advance notice of a series of early English texts designed by Bruce Rogers to include "Beowulf," "The Robin Hood Ballads," "The Life of Saint George," "Treatise on the Blazing Arms," "Morte d'Arthur," "The Canterbury Tales," and others. Broadside advertisement for the first, "The Lyf of Saynt George," with integral order form and envelope laid in.
  - Prospectus and retrospectus of the book published by the Nonesuch Press 1923-1925 in limited and ordinary editions, 36380; 2 copies
  - A catalogue. With extracts from our history, 1936; 38570; 2 copies
    Small 8vo, pp. vi; self-wrappers, fine. Titles listed include "The Constitution of the United States" and Abraham Lincoln's "Famous Speeches". Order form laid in.
  - Carruth, Hayden: The Norfolk poems...[1 June to 1 September 1961], 38516; 2 copies
    Author: Carruth, Hayden
    Broadside, folio (303 mm.); text printed in green-grey and black; previous folds, else fine. Integral order form printed on prospectus verso.
  - Hamady, Walter: Gabberjab number (5) five...for Mother's Day, 1981; 38448; 2 copies
    Broadside, square 8vo (201 mm.); printed on green paper; fine. Prospectus for the Press's 100th book, "a collage book of two footnoted poems".
  - Wakoski, [Diane and Ellen] Lanyon: Making a sacher torte, 1981; 38460; 2 copies
    Author: Wakoski, [Diane and Ellen] Lanyon
    Broadside, square 8vo (214 mm.); printed on purple paper; fine. Prospectus for a collection of 9 poems by Wakoski with illustrations by Lanyon combined "in this thematically united book about food and cooking, eating and drinking".
  - Caroll, Lewis: Looking-glass, 1982; 38416; 2 copies
    Author: Caroll, Lewis
    Hatfield, Massachusetts: Pennyroyal Press
    Long folio (560 mm.); illustration; text printed in blue and black; previous fold, else fine. Prospectus for a new edition of Carroll's "What Alice Found Through the Looking-Glass"; illustrated with wood-engravings by Barry Moser. Distributed by Taurus Books.
  - Hammer, Victor: Manifesto. Type design in relation to language and to the art of the punch cutter. Foreword by Carolyn Reading Hammer. Wood engraving by John De Pol. Chronology and specimen settings of the Uncial alphabets, 1987; 38497; 2 copies
    Author: Hammer, Victor
    Maple Shades, New Jersey: Pickering Press
    Bifolium, 4to; black and white photographic illustration tipped in; text printed in brown and black; fine. Prospectus for Hammer's work in which he "explains his philosophy of letter design; his belief that the 'maker of letters' should work in the service of the language". Edition limited to 50 copies. Small Broadside announcing a special edition of ten copies laid in.
  - Tidcombe, Marianne: The Doves Bindery., 1991; 36317; 2 copies
    Author: Tidcombe, Marianne
    New Castle, DE: Oak Knoll Books
    Sheet folded into six-sided brochure, 8vo; color photographic illustration The tale of King Florus and the fair Jehane (1893) from the Doves Bindery to front cover. Prospectus to a companion piece to Marianne Tidcombe's The bookbindings of T.J. Cobden-Sanderson, in which "Dr Tidcombe gives a detailed history of the Bindery, followed by a complete catalogue of the books, over 120 of which are described in full and illustrated (18 in colour." The work includes separate chapters on the Kelmscott Chaucer, Pupils of the Bindery, and Binding Doves Press books. Also provides "a limited quantity of folded, collated and untrimmed sets of sheets...available for sale". Brochure also includes order form, publicity for Tidcombe's earlier work on T.J. Cobden-Sanderson, and an announcement for the Doves Bindery exhibition in the King's Library, The British Library galleries, 5 April-7 July 1991.
  - The Book of Revelation. Illustrations & text of the final chapter of the New Testament by St. John the Divine. Original linoleum cuts by Barbara Benish, 1994; 37637; 2 copies
    Bifolium, 4to; illustrated prospectus providing thorough information about the conception of the book, the artist, text, design, illustrations, typography, and materials. Second copy has a typed progress report, announcement of a woodblock portfolio by Mary Allan, and a printout of Barbara Benish's resume.
  - The book of revelation, 1995; 38373; 2 copies
    Broadside, 8vo (216 mm.); color photographic illustrations; edges a bit toned, else fine. Second copy is much less toned. Prospectus for a limited edition of 50 copies, linoleum cuts Barbara Benish, illumination by Robin Price.
  - Shakespeare, William: Shakespeare's sonnets. Edited with introduction and notes by Tucker Brooke, 1936; 39407; 2 copies
    Bifolium, small 8vo; a bit toned, previous folds, else fine. Prospectus states: "The present edition seeks to show that the Quarto of Shakespeare's Sonnets in 1609, while textually faithful to the poet's manuscript, obscured its general meaning by transposing a number of the sonnet groups". Provides 2 specimen pages and integral order form.
  - Klinefelter, Walter: A small display of old maps and plans, 1962; 38519; 2 copies
    Author: Klinefelter, Walter
    Bifolium, 16mo; text printed in red and black; fine. Prospectus advertising this work as a collection of stamps "whose designs reproduce, or call to mind, maps that were first executed in the days of exploration and discovery, and plans that were drawn for the establishment of towns and the building of fortifications". Integral order form printed on back.
  - [Catalogue], 1972; 38499; 2 copies
    12mo, unpaginated; woodcut vignette; leaves unbound, fine. List of titles available "as of Summer 1972"; these include Kenneth M. Johnson's "Aerial California" and Frances J. Brewer's "The Fables of Jean de la Fontaine". Dawson's Book Shop, distributor.
  - Bly, Robert: Six winter privacy poems, 1972; 37552; 2 copies
    Author: Bly, Robert
    Broadside, 8vo (223 mm.); edition limited to 250 copies, illustrated by Karyl Klopp. 1 copy is pasted to a sheet of white paper, the other has a label addressed to the print department of the Museum of Modern Art.
  - Wakoski, Diane: The wandering tattler. Six poems/one fable...with eleven illustrations by Ellen Lanyon, 1974; 38457; 2 copies
    Broadside, long 4to (335 mm.); illustration; previous fold, else fine. Prospectus for this limited edition of 130 copies. "Easily, this is the most sumptuous book so far issued from this press."
  - Hilberry, Conrad: Housemarks, 1980; 38453; 2 copies
    Author: Hilberry, Conrad